**Emil Haines** 

www.linkedin.com/in/emilhaines/ www.github.com/emilhaines emilhaines.github.io/

A highly self-motivated PhD student with over three years experience working for international particle physics experiments. Proficient in software development and data analysis using Python and C++, with experience using modern deep learning techniques and frameworks. Hoping to transfer the skills I have acquired in research to a machine learning role within industry.

## EXPERIENCE

# ATLAS Experiment, CERN

PhD Researcher May 2021 - present

- Qualified author for ATLAS, a leading, international particle physics experiment based at CERN
- Developing and maintaining an analysis framework (C++ and Python), version controlled with git, incorporating signal selection algorithms for the study of exotic decays of the Higgs Boson to long-lived particles
- Experience analysing petabyte-scale datasets produced via particle collisions at the Large Hadron Collider and interpreting results using advanced statistical techniques
- o Graph neural networks for classification; algorithm development and performance optimisation (Pytorch)
- Completed a one year attachment at CERN (Oct. 2021 Sep. 2022), during which I undertook shifts as an on-call expert and regularly presented research to fellow students and academics
- o Contributions due to be published in high impact physics journals

## Graphcore

Silicon Engineer Intern

July - Sep. 2019

- o 10 week paid internship in the Silicon Verification team on data analytics and visualisation
- o Presented work to the CEO, CTO and VPs of the company, as well as fellow interns

# UCL

Post Graduate Teaching Assistant

Oct. 2020 - May 2021, Jan. 2024 - present

Email: emilhaines@hotmail.co.uk

Mobile: +447905567584

- $\circ$  Responsibilities: running problem classes for  $\sim$ 20 students; assisting in teaching during demonstration sessions; marking and providing feedback on coursework
- Courses: (3<sup>rd</sup> year) Practical Machine Learning for Physicists, Nuclear and Particle Physics, (1<sup>st</sup> year) Practical Physics and Computing

#### EDUCATION

#### UCL

PhD in Particle Physics

Oct. 2020 - present

- $\circ$  STFC funded research project working on the detection of new particles as a member of the ATLAS experiment
- Participated in postgraduate courses in Machine Learning for Big Data, to further my practical understanding of modern machine learning tools and techniques and database technologies, and Statistical Analysis

### University of Bristol

MSci in Physics

Sep. 2016 - June 2020

- o Graduated with first class honours, with an overall mark of 77%
- Awarded commendation for master's project entitled 'Deep Learning for event classification at LUX-ZEPLIN', for which I developed a convolutional autoencoder for detecting waveforms in time-series data (Tensorflow)
- Consistently achieved high marks in computational and mathematical units, including: 91 in Methods of Theoretical Physics, 84 in Advanced Quantum Physics and 83 in Quantum Information Theory and Computational Physics

### OTHER EXPERIENCE AND INTERESTS

- Undertook part-time roles during my undergraduate degree including: teaching Maths, English and Science to primary, GCSE and A-level students and working in hospitality at the Clifton Pavilion in Bristol Zoo
- Enjoy playing football, running, volunteering at music festivals and am currently teaching myself to play drums